{
    "name": "Panchayati Raj",
    "questions": [
        {
            "question": "The subject of Panchayati Raj is in",
            "options": [
                "A. Concurrent List",
                "B. Union List",
                "C. State List",
                "D. Residual List"
            ],
            "answer": "C. State List"
        },
        {
            "question": "The decision to conduct Panchayat Elections is taken by which of the following?",
            "options": [
                "A. The Central Government",
                "B. The State Government",
                "C. The District Judge",
                "D. The Election Commission"
            ],
            "answer": "B. The State Government"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was the first Panchayati Raj Act implemented in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1935",
                "B. 1948",
                "C. 1952",
                "D. 1974"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1948"
        },
        {
            "question": "Assam's first Panchayati Raj legislation namely Assam Rural Panchayat Act, was passed in which year?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1945",
                "B. 1948",
                "C. 1950",
                "D. 1953"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1948"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following articles is related to Panchayati Raj?",
            "options": [
                "A. Article 243",
                "B. Article 324",
                "C. Article 124",
                "D. Article 73"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Article 243"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following committees recommended the Panchayati Raj System in India?",
            "options": [
                "A. Punchhi Samiti",
                "B. Balwantrai Mehta Committee",
                "C. Singhvi Committee",
                "D. None of the following"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Balwantrai Mehta Committee"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which one of the following Amendments of the Constitution of India deals with the issue of strengthening of the Panchayati Raj?",
            "options": [
                "A. 42nd",
                "B. 44th",
                "C. 73rd",
                "D. 86th"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 73rd"
        },
        {
            "question": "The list of items which may be entrusted to the Panchayats is given in the:",
            "options": [
                "A. Tenth Schedule",
                "B. Eleventh Schedule",
                "C. Twelfth Schedule",
                "D. Seventh Schedule"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Eleventh Schedule"
        },
        {
            "question": "On which date, National Panchayati Raj Day is observed?",
            "options": [
                "A. January 28",
                "B. February 26",
                "C. March 11",
                "D. April 24"
            ],
            "answer": "D. April 24"
        },
        {
            "question": "When the Two-tier panchayat system i.e. primary panchayat and rural panchayat was adopted in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1948",
                "B. 1950",
                "C. 1956",
                "D. 1983"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1948"
        },
        {
            "question": "Panchayati Raj was started in the country in:",
            "options": [
                "A. 1951",
                "B. 1952",
                "C. 1957",
                "D. 1959"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1959"
        },
        {
            "question": "When the Three-tier panchayat system was adopted in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1986",
                "B. 1992",
                "C. 1996",
                "D. 2001"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1986"
        },
        {
            "question": "Balwant Rai Mehta Committee suggested that the structure of Panchayati Raj should consist of:",
            "options": [
                "A. The village, the block and the district levels",
                "B. The mandal and the district levels",
                "C. The village, the district and the State levels",
                "D. The village, the mandal, the district and the State levels"
            ],
            "answer": "A. The village, the block and the district levels"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Panchayati Raj System was adopted to:",
            "options": [
                "A. Make people aware of politics",
                "B. Decentralise the power of democracy",
                "C. Educate the peasants",
                "D. None of the above"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Decentralise the power of democracy"
        },
        {
            "question": "When the first panchayat election was held in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1990",
                "B. 1992",
                "C. 1996",
                "D. 2001"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1992"
        },
        {
            "question": "How many tiers are in the Panchayati Raj system of India?",
            "options": [
                "A. One-tier",
                "B. Two-tier",
                "C. Three-tier",
                "D. Four-tier"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Three-tier"
        },
        {
            "question": "A three-tier Panchayat is envisaged for states having a population above__________?",
            "options": [
                "A. 10 lakhs",
                "B. 15 lakhs",
                "C. 20 lakhs",
                "D. 25 lakhs"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 20 lakhs"
        },
        {
            "question": "What is Zila Parishad?",
            "options": [
                "A. District Panchayat",
                "B. Block Panchayat",
                "C. Gram Sabha",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "A. District Panchayat"
        },
        {
            "question": "At which level does Zila Parishad actually make development plans?",
            "options": [
                "A. District level",
                "B. Panchayat Samiti",
                "C. Block-level",
                "D. Government level"
            ],
            "answer": "A. District level"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following systems is established on the basis of direct election?",
            "options": [
                "A. Gram Panchayat",
                "B. Block Committee",
                "C. Zila Parishad",
                "D. Both B and C"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Gram Panchayat"
        },
        {
            "question": "When Assam Gana Parishad formed",
            "options": [
                "A. 14 October 1985",
                "B. 15 August 1985",
                "C. 16 December 1985",
                "D. 18 August 1985"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 14 October 1985"
        },
        {
            "question": "How many posts are reserved for women at all levels in the Panchayati raj system?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1/3",
                "B. 1/2",
                "C. 2/3",
                "D. 1/4"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1/3"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Quorum for a meeting of the Gaon Panchayat is",
            "options": [
                "A. 1/10 of the total members",
                "B. 1/5 of the total members",
                "C. 1/4 of the total members",
                "D. 1/3 of the total members"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1/10 of the total members"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following is NOT a member of Zilla Parishad?",
            "options": [
                "A. President of Gaon Panchayat",
                "B. Presidents of the Anchalik Panchayats",
                "C. Members of Lok Sabha",
                "D. Member of Legislative Assembly"
            ],
            "answer": "A. President of Gaon Panchayat"
        },
        {
            "question": "In Assam, how many subjects are assigned to Panchayat?",
            "options": [
                "A. 21 subjects",
                "B. 29 subjects",
                "C. 39 subjects",
                "D. 27 subjects"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 29 subjects"
        },
        {
            "question": "Under which article of the Indian Constitution, the Assam State Finance Commission was set up to review the financial position of the Panchayats and to make recommendations in this regard?",
            "options": [
                "A. Article 371-B",
                "B. Article 356",
                "C. Article 359",
                "D. Article 243-1"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Article 243-1"
        },
        {
            "question": "The source of the maximum income to Panchayati Raj institution is:",
            "options": [
                "A. Local taxes",
                "B. Regional funds",
                "C. Government grants",
                "D. Share in Union Govt. Revenue"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Government grants"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following is NOT a source of funds for Gaon Panchayat?",
            "options": [
                "A. Transfer by State Finance Commission for development purpose",
                "B. Loan from Banks",
                "C. Own Sources of Revenue (Tax and Non-Taxes)",
                "D. Contribution by the communities themselves"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Loan from Banks"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which is the apex level under the three-tier Panchayati Raj system in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Gaon Panchayat",
                "B. Anchalik Panchayat",
                "C. Zilla Parishad",
                "D. Nagar panchayats"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Zilla Parishad"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who is to conduct the elections to the Panchayats and Municipalities?",
            "options": [
                "A. State Government",
                "B. Central Government",
                "C. State Election Commission",
                "D. Central Election Commission"
            ],
            "answer": "C. State Election Commission"
        },
        {
            "question": "A Municipal Corporation is set up in a city with a population of not less than:",
            "options": [
                "A. 1 lakh",
                "B. 12 lakh",
                "C. 10 lakh",
                "D. 5 lakh"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 10 lakh"
        },
        {
            "question": "In the Assam Panchayat election, what percent of seats are reserved for women?",
            "options": [
                "A. 67 percent",
                "B. 50 percent",
                "C. 33 percent",
                "D. 25 percent"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 50 per cent"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which is the apex level under the three-tier Panchayati Raj system in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Gaon Panchayat",
                "B. Anchalik Panchayat",
                "C. Zilla Parishad",
                "D. Nagar panchayats"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Zilla Parishad"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following is not a member of Zilla Parishad?",
            "options": [
                "A. President of Gaon Panchayat",
                "B. Presidents of the Anchalik Panchayats",
                "C. Members of Lok Sabha",
                "D. Member of Legislative Assembly"
            ],
            "answer": "A. President of Gaon Panchayat"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first state to ratify Central Govt's GST Bill",
            "options": [
                "A. Rajasthan",
                "B. Madhya Pradesh",
                "C. Assam",
                "D. Chhattisgarh"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Assam"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which Schedule of the Indian Constitution deals with administrative provisions of tribal areas in Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram?",
            "options": [
                "A. First",
                "B. Sixth",
                "C. Second",
                "D. Twelfth"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Sixth"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which article of the Constitution of Indian has a special provision with respect to the State of Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Article 371",
                "B. Article 371B",
                "C. Article 273",
                "D. Article 300"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Article 371B"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which tier of the Panchayati Raj system in Assam is responsible for preparing an integrated plan for the district as well as urban and rural areas?",
            "options": [
                "A. Geon Panchayat",
                "B. Anchalik Panchayat",
                "C. Zilla Parishad",
                "D. All of these"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Zilla Parishad"
        },
        {
            "question": "How many Zilla Parishads does Assam have presently?",
            "options": [
                "A. 20",
                "B. 21",
                "C. 36",
                "D. 54"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 21"
        },
        {
            "question": "How many Gaon Panchayats are there in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1500",
                "B. 1681",
                "C. 1876",
                "D. 2201"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 2201"
        },
        {
            "question": "How many Anchalik Panchayats are there in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 150",
                "B. 158",
                "C. 185",
                "D. 220"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 185"
        },
        {
            "question": "Special representation in Panchayati Raj Institutions is given to",
            "options": [
                "A. Women",
                "B. Co-operative societies",
                "C. Backward classes",
                "D. All of the above"
            ],
            "answer": "D. All of the above"
        },
        {
            "question": "A person to be qualified for standing in a panchayat election must have attained the age of",
            "options": [
                "A. 21 years",
                "B. 18 years",
                "C. 25 years",
                "D. 30 years"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 21 years"
        },
        {
            "question": "The elections to Panchayats are to be held:",
            "options": [
                "A. Every four years",
                "B. Every five years",
                "C. When the State Government decides to do so",
                "D. At the Centers directive"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Every five years"
        }
    ]
}
